Register of the Margaret Eleanor Fait Papers, 1945-1946
Hoover Institution Archives
Margaret Eleanor Fait Papers,
1945-1946
84040
Fait, Margaret Eleanor
5 manuscript boxes, 18 envelopes (3.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Reports, dispatches, memoranda, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to relief aid to displaced persons in Germany at the end of World War II, and to Jewish refugees in transit to Palestine.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; International relief.; Jews.; Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Germany.
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1945-46 (Boxes 1-5)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, bulletins, studies, questionnaires, printed matter and photographs, collected by M. E. Fait as Public Relations Officer, United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, U.S. Zone, Germany, 1945-46.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 307 prints / 18 envelopes (Box 84040 - 10.A-V)
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE, 1945-46
  - Aley, A., "U.N.R.R.A. - Nothing But the Truth," September 16, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allied Expeditionary Force, Displaced Persons Registration Instructions, June 1944 (Folder 2)
  - American Council for Judaism (Folder 3)
  - American Red Cross activities in Western Europe, 1944-47 (Folder 4)
  - Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry, Report to the U.S. Government and His Majesty's Government in the U.K., Lausanne, Switzerland, April 20, 1946 (Folder 5)
  - Buchenwald concentration camp (Folder 6)
  - Displaced persons
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Children (Folder 8-9)
    - Education (Folder 10)
    - Emigration (Folder 11)
    - Expellees (Folder 12)
    - Food (Folder 13)
    - Jews (Folder 14)
    - Jews (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Jewish children sent to Palestine (Folder 4)
    - Latvians (Folder 5)
    - Law and order (Folder 6)
    - Mennonite controversy (Folder 7)
    - Poles (Folder 8)
    - Polish repatriation efforts (Folder 9)
    - Postwar developments (Folder 10)
    - Questionnaires upon which the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry Report was based, 1946 (Folder 11)
    - Questionnaires upon which the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry Report was based, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
    - Russians (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Screening (Folder 2)
    - Tracing services (Folder 3)
    - Van Velsen, A. F. (Folder 4)
  - Displaced Persons Commission, Second Semiannual Report to the President and Congress, August 1, 1949 (Folder 5)
  - Displaced Persons Operation, U.S. Zone, Germany, Summary Report, 6/11/45 (Folder 6)
  - Fye, Colonel (Folder 7)
  - Germany, postwar conditions (Folder 8)
  - Latvia (Folder 9)
  - Meader, George, excerpt from Confidential Report to the Special Senate Committee Investigating the National Defense Program on the Preliminary Investigation of Military Government in Occupied Areas of Europe, 22 November 1946 (Folder 10)
  - Office of Military Government for Germany (US)
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Economics Division, "A Year of Potsdam - The German Economy Since the Surrender," n.d. (Folder 12)
  - Supreme Headquarters. Allied Expeditionary Force.
    - Civil Affairs Division, Guide to Assembly Center Administration
      - Displaced Persons Branch, July 1944 (Folder 13)
      - Displaced Persons, Refugees, and Welfare Branch, revised September 1944 (Folder 14)
    - Guide to the Care of Displaced Persons in Germany, May 1945 (Folder 15)
  - Transfer of German population from Czechoslovakia to the U.S. Zone, Germany, 1945-46 (Folder 16)
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA)
    - Agreement as to the Relationship of UNRRA to the Commanding General USFET in the U.S. Zone of Germany, 19 February 1946 (Folder 17)
    - Basic Field Manual, Part II, Personnel Policy and Procedure, 3 January 1946 (Folder 18)
    - Central Headquarters for Germany
      - Public Information Office (Folder 19)
      - Weekly situation reports, November-December 1945 (Folder 20)
    - Committee of the Council for Europe (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Displaced persons camps, map of (Folder 2)
    - Displaced Persons Division, Handbook on Procedure for Registration of Displaced Persons, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Displaced Persons Operation in Germany
      - General (Folder 4)
      - December holidays (Folder 5)
      - Weekly report, June 10-16, 1945 (Folder 6)
    - European Regional Office
      - General (Folder 7)
      - Personnel Field Regulations, December 10, 1945 (Folder 8)
    - German Operations
      - 1945 (Folder 9)
      - Public Information Section (Folder 10)
    - Grigsby, Robert, Team 55, "Applied Economics for Displaced Persons," n.d. (Folder 11)
    - Statement by Director Herbert H. Lehman (Folder 12)
    - Team 303, Welfare Section (Folder 13)
    - Team 502, Stuttgart (Folder 14)
    - Team reports, 1945 (Folder 15)
    - United Nations Displaced Persons Operation, American Occupied Territory, Germany (Folder 16)
    - UNRRA - Organization, Aims, Progress, 1944 (Folder 17)
    - U.S. Zone Headquarters, Wiesbaden
      - General (Folder 18)
      - Polish children, 1945 (Folder 19)
      - Public Relations Office (Folder 20)
      - Team bulletins, 1945 (Folder 21)
      - Ukrainian theatrical group (Folder 22)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 23)
  - U.S. Forces, European Theater Headquarters
    - Nationalities, determination and reporting of, 1945 (Folder 24)
    - Office of Military Government (U.S. Zone), Displaced Persons Division (Folder 25)
    - Postal service between DPs in the U.S. Zone and the United States, 1945 (Folder 26)
    - Procedure for care of United Nations displaced persons, August 31, 1945 (Folder 27)
    - Public Relations Division, 1945-46 (Folder 28)
    - UNRRA in the U.S. Zone, Meade Committee Report, 1946 (Folder 29)
  - United States War Department, Basic Field Manual - Military Government (Folder 30)
  - World's YMCA-YWCA, "Two Years With Displaced Persons," n.d. (Folder 31)
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 84040 - 10.A-V)
  - 15 photos depicting children in displaced persons (DP) camps. Germany., undated (Folder A)
  - 34 photos depicting Aglasterhausen DP camp in Germany., undated (Folder B)
  - 31 photos depicting employment projects in DP camps in Germany., undated (Folder C)
  - 26 photos depicting education in DP camps in Germany, undated (Folder D)
  - 12 photos depicting medical attention in DP camps, Germany, undated (Folder E)
  - 49 photos depicting living conditions in DP camps, Germany., undated (Folder F-G)
  - 5 photos depicting administration of DP camps, Germany., undated (Folder H)
  - 39 photos depicting arts and crafts in DP camps, Germany., undated (Folder I-J)
  - 10 prints depicting a textbook project for DP camp schools, Germany., undated (Folder K)
  - 16 prints depicting DPs as students at Heidelberg University, Germany., undated (Folder L)
  - 16 prints depicting religious activities in DP camps, Germany., undated (Folder M)
  - 7 prints depicting the shipment of Jews to Palestine from DP camps, Germany., undated (Folder N)
  - 16 prints depicting Poles returning to Poland from DP camps in Germany., undated (Folder O)
  - 17 prints depicting United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) activities in Poland after World War II., undated (Folder P)
  - 11 prints depicting UNRRA agricultural projects in Poland after World War II., undated (Folder Q)
  - 3 prints depicting scenes of World War II destruction in Wiesbaden, Germany., undated (Folder R)